I've never heard of this ethereal
molecule before. How does one pronounce
it? Is it
creatine? Apparently, Dr. Rhonda Patrick
had a creatine researcher, Dr. Kandow,
on her podcast wherein he makes the
argument for why five grams, the dose
told to almost everyone, is not enough,
and why creatine may not provide benefit
for some, but provide noticeable benefit
for others. Dr. Patrick in her usual
fashion provides references. So, we'll
pop open those studies and see what's
what, as well as find out if 5 g really
isn't enough. Let's listen in. Now, our
brain is small from stature, but it uses
20% of our daily energy. And of course,
as we all know, when you're really
tired, sleep deprivation, running
around, chasing your children, most
people that I know are really
metabolically stressed, primarily from a
cognition perspective. And that's where
creatine seems to have the best lines of
evidence. sleep deprivation, hypoxia, I
jetlag. I was up at 3:00 this morning
and flew down. So, I'll be taking a
really high dose today to hopefully
offset the the chance of inflammation or
uh cognitive decline. Um, so when we
look at the totality of emerging
evidence, it's split. Some studies don't
see any effect, but the ones that do is
in a population where they're either
mentally fatigued, sleep deprivation, or
during times of aging. And that's where
memory comes into play. Well, I already
have an issue with this, but in short,
we're discussing the brain, which is a
newer frontier for creatine research.
Most research has been focused on muscle
and physical performance, but now
researchers have been realizing
creatine's effects on multiple organ
systems. The idea although this is a
simplified version is that creatine gets
taken up into our cells let's say brain
cells like the neurons and from there
the creatine molecule can be
phosphorolated or tagged with a
phosphate molecule in doing so it gets
turned into phosphocreatine. This
matters because the phosphocreatine is a
reserve energy system inside your cells.
when the cells need immediate energy it
can rely for a few seconds on
phosphocreatine to generate extremely
quick cellular energy. So the more
creatine molecules in the brain cells,
the more phosphocreatine potential and
the greater the cell's energy buffer.
Dr. Dr. Kandow makes an excellent point
that creatine's effectiveness in the
brain is not generally detected in
people who are not cognitively stressed,
but it is detected in people who are
doing cognitively stressing tests or
they're older. So, generally over the
age of 60. I've mentioned this in
previous analyses myself. However, where
I push back is using this reference as
evidence. This meta analysis is not a
good one. And we can see clear evidence
of that here. This is a force plot with
all of the studies included in the
analysis. On the left side, they're
comparing creatine groups against
non-creatine groups on a measure of
memory. That black diamond on the bottom
indicates an effect because it doesn't
cross the neutral zero line running down
the middle. Great. Now, I'm a little
confused, but it isn't explained why it
moves in favor of the control, but the
researchers clearly state that it's
creatine that experiences the benefit.
Maybe it's a timebased test, so longer
is worse. Anyway, doesn't matter. Let's
assume that it's correct. If we look at
the studies on the left side, again,
they made a massive mistake by including
the same study over and over again. The
most egregious example is the Alvis
study and the McMorris studies. The
reason they included the same study
repeatedly is because they're including
different measurements, but that's an
improper inclusion because you're
measuring the same outcome. So you're
effectively counting the same group of
participants seven times, which
massively inflates the number of
participants included in the analysis,
and it finds an artificial effect when
if we were to remove most of these
studies, we'd likely see a complete loss
of the memory effect. In fact, on other
outcomes like processing speed and other
cognitive outcomes, we see creatine has
no effect according to the same
analysis. So, the effect is likely only
due to this hyperinflated data. Does
that then mean there's no effect of
creatine? No. I've covered other
analyses that corrected for this problem
and still found an effect. And I've also
covered multiple independent randomized
control trials that also show effects
exactly as Dr. Kandell describes. Now, I
just wouldn't use this previous analysis
because it's just not a very good one.
Okay. So, creatine helps those that are
in cognitively demanding positions or
older over 60. But let's get a little
more into the how creatine causes these
effects on the brain and then we'll get
into dosing. And the common denominator
seems to be the more that the brain is
stressed, the more creatine seems to
come to the rescue. Same analogy from a
muscle and bone perspective. So uh we
can talk for hours just on the brain and
uh it's a very exciting area for sure.
The idea behind creatine's effectiveness
in a bit more detail is the fact that
when we're using our old noggin up here,
the brain mass consumes cellular energy
called ATP. These ATP stores can drop
within seconds when a neuron activates
because millions of enzymes consume ATP
to allow the neuron to function. As
such, creatine through this phosphor
creatine system that we described a bit
ago can donate phosphates from itself to
refphospholate or reattach phosphates to
spent ATP molecules creating new ATP
molecules. That means that the cells are
able to activate again more quickly
offering a cognitive advantage. Okay. So
why is more creatine better? So the
brain is stressed. So, so brain aging
older adults. That's that's that's aging
is a stress on the brain. It is. So,
supplementing with how much creatine can
improve cognition in let's say older
adults. Yeah. As little as about five
grams has been shown to have some
potential. But this is interesting. I
just you know 20 minutes ago said that
the loading phase wasn't needed for
muscle. The best studies for the brain
look at 20 grams a day for at least a
week. So now you're in a conundrum by
looking at muscle, bone, and brain. And
the theory here is that since the bloodb
brain barrier is very resistant to
creatine and unfortunately we have this
really important gal cell called
astroytes which are the most the biggest
in in our uh central nervous system. It
sort of acts as a filter from our blood
into our cells and it really determine
what gets in and it says hey foreign
pathogens no you're not getting into the
the neuron or the cell. Uh so
unfortunately they don't have the
creatine transporter or doorway. The
reason five grams the standard dose up
to now is insufficient is because the
blood levels are too low to cross the
bloodb brain barrier or at least make a
huge difference on brain levels. That's
because the bloodb brain barrier is
walled off by cells called aststerytes.
These astroytes have feet that extend
down to create a barrier along with the
endothelial cells facing the
bloodstream. These aststerytes have
limited or no ability to produce the
creatine transporter according to this
review and therefore can't allow
creatine through. So then how does
creatine still get through at higher
concentrations when we consume more than
5 g? Well, that's the question. I don't
think we know yet or at least I don't.
And I did look for an answer in the
literature. We know the first lining of
cells, the endothelial cells do express
the creatine transporter. So they can be
taken up there, but that still leaves
the astroite wall. It's possible that
the barrier isn't completely impermeable
if the creatine concentrations are very
high. But we don't have a complete
understanding yet. Where does that leave
us on dosing then? You know, I wrote a
book on creatine. I don't sell it
anymore, but it is available along with
a guide on how to approach creatine
dosing in various situations. I'm
including in the extended version of
this video that you're watching. Both
along with live sessions, podcasts, a
library of videos, detailed articles,
shortened summaries, is available over
at the Physionic Insiders. You can join
through the link in the description. But
beware, you may need some additional
creatine considering the sheer amount of
learning that we do over there. I hope
to see you there.
So, what are the amounts to consume if
not 5 grams? Well, I said this over two
years ago in my analysis on creatine and
the brain. I didn't have strong proof
except that some other researchers were
using upwards of 20 grams per day. Dr.
Kandow mentions going up to 20 grams,
maybe even more. And that's because you
have to raise blood levels sufficiently
to force some into the brain, assuming
that we're discussing the brain only
here. I will say I have also reviewed
studies indicating five grams shows
benefits even for the brain. But if you
wanted to be on the safe side, 20 grams
would be more consistent of an effect
likely. So overall, when discussing the
brain, there's some evidence, although I
still wouldn't call it strong evidence,
that 20 gram of creatine might be better
than five grams of creatine. I'd like to
see more research, research like that
that I describe right here.